Arnold Moss Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Arnold Moss Papers 1935-1987 (bulk 1953-1987)
MSS33738
Moss, Arnold, 1910-1989
2,100 items
11 containers
4.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Actor, director, theatrical producer, and crossword puzzle maker. Correspondence, contracts, scripts, playbills and programs, financial records, speeches, writings, drafts of crossword puzzles, and printed matter documenting Moss's career primarily as a stage actor, producer, and director.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Burton, Philip, 1904- --Correspondence.; Malamud, Bernard--Correspondence.; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005--Correspondence.; Moss, Arnold, 1910-1989.; Prince, Harold, 1928-2019--Correspondence.; Shaw, Bernard, 1866-1950. Back to Methuselah (1946)
Organizations
Library of Congress.; Shakespeare Festival Players; United States. Department of State.
Subjects
Acting.; Crossword puzzles.; Drama.; Repertory theater.; Theater--Africa.; Theater--Far East.; Theater--Latin America.; Theater--Production and direction.; Universities and colleges.
Occupations
Actors.; Crossword puzzle makers.; Theatrical producers.
Provenance
The papers of Arnold Moss, actor, director, theatrical producer, and crossword puzzle maker, were presented by him to the Library of Congress as gifts during the years 1966-1975 and as deposits 1975-1987. The deposits were converted to gifts in 1999.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Sound recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Arnold Moss Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Arnold Moss are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1910, Jan. 28 Born, Brooklyn, N. Y.
1928 A.B., College of the City of New York (later City College of the City University of New York), New York, N.Y.
1929 1931 Apprenticeship, Eva Le Gallienne's Civic Repertory Theatre, New York, N.Y.
1931 Broadway debut, Wonder Boy, Alvin Theatre, New York, N.Y.
1933 Married Stella Reynolds
1933 1940 Instructor, Speech and Theatre Department, Brooklyn College, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1934 A.M., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1940 First major role on Broadway, The Fifth Column, Alvin Theatre, New York, N.Y.
1946 Film debut, Temptation
1954 1974 Appeared in programs of dramatic readings and performances as part of the Gertrude Clarke Whittall Poetry and Literature Series, Library of Congress
1957 1958 Adapted, coproduced, and acted in George Bernard Shaw's Back to Methuselah on tour and on Broadway, New York, N.Y.
1959 Founded, directed, and starred in Shakespeare Festival Players, a touring repertory company
1961 American specialist in theater, Department of State, Central America and South America
1964 American specialist in theater, Department of State, Africa and the Far East
1973 Ph.D., New York University, New York, N.Y.
1973 1974 Visiting professor, Department of Dramatic Arts, University of Connecticut, Storrs, Conn.
1975 Visiting professor, Pace University, New York, N.Y. Writer, actor, "CBS Radio Mystery Theatre"
1976 Visiting professor, Eminent Scholar Program, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Va.
1977 Visiting professor, Purdue University, West Lafayette, Ind.
1983 1984 National Visiting Scholar, Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences
1989, Dec. 15 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Arnold Moss (1910-1989) span the years 1935-1987 with the bulk of the material covering the period 1953-1987. Although Moss's acting career included roles in film and on radio and television, with related work as a narrator and an announcer, the main focus of his work was on the stage. Likewise, the main focus of the Moss Papers is on his roles in the theater as an actor, director, producer, and educator. Moss gained particular acclaim for his performances in the plays of William Shakespeare. This collection of his papers consists of three series: General Correspondence, Theater File, and Subject File.
The General Correspondence series, 1954-1987, documents Moss's interests and activities primarily as they relate to his career. The major portion consists of letters received from friends and professional colleagues, although copies of letters sent are also included. Topics include efforts to gain employment as an actor, his work at colleges and universities, and his affiliation with professional organizations. Prominent correspondents include Philip Burton, Bernard Malamud, Arthur Miller, and Harold Prince.
The Theater File, 1953-1987, comprises the largest portion of the papers and reflects the range of Moss's stage work. There are lengthy files on George Bernard Shaw's play, Back to Methuselah, which Moss adapted into a shorter version and coproduced with the Theatre Guild for a tour and Broadway run in 1957-1958. Moss also acted in the production, playing Shaw. The following year Moss founded and starred in a touring repertory company called the Shakespeare Festival Players. Records relating to the company include contracts, an itinerary, financial files, and press clippings. Also documented in the file is Moss's position as an American specialist in theater for the United States Department of State. He toured countries in Central and South America and later in Africa and the Far East giving performances and lectures. Files on concert readings relate to the one-man programs of dramatic readings such as "A Goodly Heritage," "The Seven Ages of Man," and "Windows on America" that Moss performed at colleges and universities and at civic and cultural organizations from the 1950s into the 1980s. For twenty years, Moss performed annually at the Library of Congress as part of the Gertrude Clarke Whittall Poetry and Literature Series, and the related files contain correspondence, scripts, programs, and production notes. Most scripts are filed in a separate scripts section because Moss used the scripts for more than one production. The scripts are annotated, and many contain lighting and sound cues and stage diagrams.
The Subject File, 1935-1987, contains material relating to Moss's other activities, his organizational affiliations, and his academic studies. Files on film, sound recordings, and television containing information in these areas are limited, and these aspects of his career are not well documented in the collection.
In addition to his work in the performing arts, Moss created crossword puzzles appearing in the New York Times Magazine and other publications. The crossword puzzle files contain correspondence with the New York Times puzzle editors and drafts of the puzzles. Speeches and writings files contain drafts of published and unpublished articles and speeches primarily relating to the theater. The file on New York University contains material on the doctoral degree which Moss started in the 1930s and completed in the 1970s with a dissertation on professional actors as guest artists in college and university theatrical productions.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
General Correspondence, 1954-1987
Theater File, 1953-1987
Subject File, 1935-1987
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1954-1987 (Box 1-2)
  Letters received and a few letters sent.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1960-1963, 1971-1986, undated (Box 1)
  - Burton, Philip, 1970-1975, 1982-1986 (Box 1)
  - "B-G" miscellaneous, 1958-1986, undated, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Hamilton, Thomas H., 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Hewitt, Alan, 1967-1973, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - "H-K" miscellaneous, 1954-1986, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Library of Congress, 1968, 1973-1974, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - "L" miscellaneous, 1954, 1962-1979 (Box 1)
  - Malamud, Bernard, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Maleska, Eugene T., 1974, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - Miller, Arthur, 1969-1970, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Miller, Claire Glass, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - "M-O" miscellaneous, 1963-1984, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Picon, Molly, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Prince, Harold, 1972-1978, 1986 (Box 1)
  - "P" miscellaneous, 1959, 1971-1982, undated (Box 1)
  - "R-Z" miscellaneous, 1959-1987, undated, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Unidentified, 1971, undated (Box 2)
- Theater File, 1953-1987 (Box 2-9)
  Scripts, correspondence, playbills and programs, clippings, contracts, financial records, and other material relating to Moss's work in the theater.
  Arranged alphabetically by title or type of production.
  - Back To Methuselah (Box 2)
    - Box office statements, 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Contracts and agreements, 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Becker and London, 1957-1960 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1953-1966 (Box 2)
      - Society of Authors, 1956-1966 (Box 2)
      - Theatre Guild, 1953-1958, undated (Box 2)
    - Financial matters, 1957-1958, undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellany, 1958, undated (Box 3)
    - Press clippings, 1957-1958, undated (Box 3)
    - Printed matter, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Productions by others of Moss's adaptation, 1959-1966 (Box 3)
    - Scripts, 1956-1958, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Concert readings, 1957-1987, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Library of Congress performances (Box 4)
    - Basler, Roy, retirement, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1976, undated (Box 4)
    - Dramatic readings (Box 4)
      - "Come, Woo Me!" 1963, undated, 1963, undated (Box 4)
      - Love's Labour's Lost, 1959, undated (Box 4)
      - "One Man In His Time: Edwin Arlington Robinson," 1969 (Box 4)
      - "Parents and Children," 1968 (Box 4)
      - "The Year That Trembled: 1865," 1965, undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellany, 1960-1966, undated (Box 4)
    - Press, 1957-1967, 1973, undated (Box 4)
    - Programs, 1954-1973, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous productions and performances (Box 4)
    - Follies, 1972 (Box 4)
    - King Lear, University of Kentucky, Lexington, Ky., 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Love's Labour's Lost, Otterbein College, Westerville, Ohio, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Poetry Society of America, 1960-1969 (Box 4)
    - Story of a Soldier (L'Histoire du Soldat), 1953-1956 (Box 5)
    - Various roles, 1958-1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Notes, sketches, minutes, and other miscellany, 1958, 1964-1976, undated (Box 5)
  - Repertory theater proposals, 1960-1961, undated (Box 5)
  - Scripts (Box 5)
    - Back to Methuselah See Container 3, same heading (Box 5)
    - King Lear, undated, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - Love's Labour's Lost, undated, (6 folders) (Box 6)
    - Macbeth, 1965, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Measure For Measure, undated, (4 folders) (Box 7)
    - Merry Wives of Windsor, undated (Box 8)
    - The Tempest, 1957, undated, (4 folders) (Box 8)
  - Shakespeare Festival Players (Box 8)
    - Box office statements, 1959 (Box 8)
    - Cast, 1959, undated (Box 8)
    - Contracts, 1958-1959, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 8)
    - Financial matters, 1959-1961, undated (Box 8)
    - Itinerary, 1959, undated (Box 8)
    - Press clippings, 1959 (Box 8)
    - Production material, 1959, undated (Box 8)
    - Programs, 1959 (Box 9)
    - Publicity, 1959, undated (Box 9)
    - Scripts See Container 7, Measure For Measure and Container 8, The Tempest (Box 9)
  - State Department tours (Box 9)
    - Africa and the Far East, 1964-1965, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Central America and South America, 1960-1962, (4 folders) (Box 9)
    - Miscellany, 1962-1969 (Box 9)
- Subject File, 1935-1987 (Box 9-11)
  Correspondence, notes, résumés, clippings, speeches, writings, draft crossword puzzles, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of organization, topic, activity, or type of material.
  - Actors and actresses, undated (Box 9)
  - American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA), 1969-1986, undated (Box 9)
  - American Theatre Association (ATA) (Box 9)
    - General, 1973-1986 (Box 9)
    - University and College Theatre Association (UCTA), 1973-1974 (Box 9)
  - Biographical information, 1955-1980, undated (Box 9)
  - City College of the City University of New York, New York, N.Y. (Box 10)
    - General, 1968, 1975-1985 (Box 10)
    - Leonard Davis Center for the Performing Arts, 1975-1983, undated (Box 10)
  - College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Va., 1976-1977 (Box 10)
  - Crossword puzzles, 1967-1987, undated, (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Films (Box 10)
    - The Fool Killer, 1965 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 1951, 1964-1966 (Box 10)
  - Miscellany, 1937-1938, 1961-1969, 1978-1981, undated (Box 10)
  - New York University, New York, N.Y. (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1935-1940, 1970-1979 (Box 10)
    - Dissertation material, 1972, undated (Box 10)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1976-1986 (Box 11)
  - Sound recordings, 1956-1960, 1972-1979, undated (Box 11)
  - Speeches and writings, 1958-1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Television, circa 1967, 1971, 1977 (Box 11)
  - Unemployment insurance, 1966-1970, undated (Box 11)
  - Viennese Opera Ball, 1971-1976, 1983, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)